Oliver Otis Howard Papers M091 M091
George J. Mitchell Department of Special Collections & Archives, Bowdoin College Library, Brunswick, Maine 04011
- M91.8: Articles and addresses, bound volumes and scrapbooks, 1863-1866, undated, M91.8; 5.25 linear feet
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). [Encyclopedia Britannica articles on Civil War battles] (No. 28) (Box 41, Folder 66)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "Taft, Wm. Howard" (No. 29) (Box 41, Folder 67)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "Taylor, Gen. Zachary" (No. 30) (Box 41, Folder 68)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "A Typical Mountain Family" (No. 31) (Box 41, Folder 69)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "Vicksburg, Campaign of" (No. 32) (Box 41, Folder 70)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "Victoria, Indian Chief" (No. 33) (Box 41, Folder 71)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "Wallace, Gen. Lew" (No. 34) (Box 41, Folder 72)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "Warfare, Secular and Christian, Past and Future" (No. 35) (Box 41, Folder 73)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "At West Point as instructor, U.S.M.A." (No. 36) (Box 41, Folder 74)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "Hazing at West Point" (No. 37) (Box 41, Folder 75)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "White Bird Canon, Battle of" (No. 38) (Box 41, Folder 76)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "The American Soldier" (No. 39) (Box 41, Folder 77)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "Christian, to become a" (No. 40) (Box 41, Folder 78)
  - [Miscellaneous and Biographical] (Vol 10). "11th Army Corps" (No. 41) (Box 41, Folder 79)
  - [Miscellaneous] (Vol 11). "Nez Perce, Expeditions against hostile Indians" (No. 1) (Box 41, Folder 80)
  - [Miscellaneous] (Vol 11). "Atlanta, the Battles of" (No. 2) (Box 41, Folder 81)
  - [Miscellaneous] (Vol 11). "Gettysburg" (No. 3) (Box 41, Folder 82)
  - [Miscellaneous] (Vol 11). "The Count and I" (No. 4) (Box 41, Folder 83)
  - [Miscellaneous] (Vol 11). "First Congregational Church" (No. 5) (Box 41, Folder 84)
  - [Miscellaneous lectures]. "Address to Medical Class - Howard University" (No. 2) (Box 41, Folder 85)
  - [Miscellaneous lectures]. "Our Christian duty towards the Southern People" (No. 3) (Box 41, Folder 86)
  - [Miscellaneous lectures]. "Personal Experience of Army Life" (No. 4) (Box 41, Folder 87)
  - [Miscellaneous lectures]. "National Education - A National Safeguard" (No. 5) (Box 41, Folder 88)
  - [Miscellaneous lectures]. "Ambition" (No. 6) (Box 41, Folder 89)
  - [Miscellaneous lectures]. "The Nation's Capital" (No. 7) (Box 41, Folder 90)
  - [Miscellaneous lectures]. "Friendship, Economy..." (No. 8) (Box 41, Folder 91)
  - [Miscellaneous articles and lectures]. [5 Articles]: 1. "A plan of life"; 2. "The danger of depreciating a boy"; 3. "Article on military subordination"; 4. "Journey through the South"; 5. "Address to the Medical Class of H.U." (Box 41, Folder 92)
  - [Miscellaneous articles and lectures]. [6 Lectures]: 1. "Five lectures on Heaven"; 2. "Unbelief - Heb. 3rd, 12th"; 3. "The worth of the Soul"; 4. "So thus every one shall give an account of himself and Rom 14:12"; 5. "Ambition"; 6. "Prayer" (No. 1) (Box 41, Folder 93)
  - [Miscellaneous articles and lectures]. [9 Lectures]: 1. "Resurrection of the Dead"; 2. "Grace"; 3. "The Confessing of Christ - John 12:42 & 43"; 4. "The Christian hope"; 5. "Prayer"; 6. "If ye continue in my Word - John 8:31 & 32"; 7. "Again the Kingdom of Heaven is like and Matt. 13:45 & 46"; 8. "Repentance - Ezek. 18:30"; 9. "Back-sliding - Jer. 3rd:22" (No. 2) (Box 41, Folder 94)
  - [Miscellaneous articles and lectures]. "Lectures on our Lord's Prayer" (No. 3) (Box 41, Folder 95)
  - [Miscellaneous articles and lectures]. "Lectures on the Commandments" (No. 4) (Box 41, Folder 96)
  - [Miscellaneous articles and lectures]. [7 Articles]: 1. "Two old Sermons", 2. "Notes for Lecture on the Capital"; 3. "Notes for Lecture on the Gospel"; 4. "Notes for Lecture on the Education in the South"; 5. "Future Life"; 6. "Columbus"; 7. "Student Life" (No. 5) (Box 41, Folder 97)
  - [Miscellaneous articles and lectures]. "Address to two Companies leaving West Point in 1858" (No. 6) (Box 41, Folder 98)
  - [Miscellaneous articles and lectures]. [6 Articles]: 1. "The new life"; 2. "Raising of the daughter of Jainus"; 3. "Faith"; 4. "To whom shall we go? - John 6:6-8"; 5. "Miracle of Cana - John 4:46-54"; 6. "Whatsoever a man soweth - Gal. 6:7" (No. 7) (Box 41, Folder 99)
- M91.9: Collection indices, 1865-1909, undated, M91.9; 2.25 linear feet
  Indexes to the correspondence files (M91.1 through M91.6), most prepared by Howard's staff for inclusion in the volumes in which the letters were once bound; also included are three volumes of abstracts of the Freedmen's Bureau correspondence received files which overlap with these. These indexes contain many inaccuracies, including omissions, misspellings and mistranscriptions of names, and incorrect pagination.
  Reproduction Note
  - [ca. 1850-1860?] (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - [mid-1865] (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - 1865 July - Aug (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - 1865 Aug 26 - Oct (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - 1865 Nov - Dec (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - 1866 Jan - Feb (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - 1866 Mar - Apr (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - 1866 May - Jun (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - 1866 Jul (Box 42, Folder 9)
  - 1866 Aug - Sep 12 (Box 42, Folder 10)
  - 1866 Sep 13 - Oct 25 (Box 42, Folder 11)
  - 1866 Oct 24 - Nov 22 (Box 42, Folder 12)
  - 1866 Nov 23 - Dec (Box 42, Folder 13)
  - 1867 Jan - Feb (Box 42, Folder 14)
  - 1867 Mar (Box 42, Folder 15)
  - 1867 Apr - May (Box 42, Folder 16)
  - 1867 May 19 - Jul 25 (Box 42, Folder 17)
  - 1867 May 10 - Jun 13 (Box 42, Folder 18)
  - 1867 Jun 13 - Jul 23 (Box 42, Folder 19)
  - 1867 Jul 23 - Aug 31 (Box 42, Folder 20)
  - 1867 Jul 25 - Sep 30 (Box 42, Folder 21)
  - 1867 Sep - Oct (Box 42, Folder 22)
  - 1867 Oct - post-1868 Jun (Box 42, Folder 23)
  - 1867 Nov - Dec (Box 42, Folder 24)
  - 1868 Jan - Feb (Box 42, Folder 25)
  - 1868 Mar - Apr 19 (Box 42, Folder 26)
  - 1868 Apr 19 - Jun 30 (Box 42, Folder 27)
  - [1868] (Box 42, Folder 28)
  - 1868 Jul - Sep (Box 42, Folder 29)
  - 1868 Sep 13 - Oct 24 (Box 42, Folder 30)
  - 1868 Sep 3 - Nov 24 (Box 42, Folder 31)
  - 1868 Nov 25 - Dec (Box 42, Folder 32)
  - [1869 Jan 9 - Mar 13?] (Box 42, Folder 33)
  - 1869 Mar 5 - Apr 16 (Box 42, Folder 34)
  - 1869 Apr 17 - May 31 (Box 42, Folder 35)
  - 1869 Jun - Jul 21 (Box 42, Folder 36)
  - 1869 Jul 22 - Aug 31 (Box 42, Folder 37)
  - 1869 Sep - Oct (Box 42, Folder 38)
  - 1869 Nov - Dec (Box 42, Folder 39)
  - 1870 Jan - Feb (Box 42, Folder 40)
  - 1870 Mar - Apr (Box 42, Folder 41)
  - 1870 May - Jul (Box 42, Folder 42)
  - 1870 Aug - Sep (Box 42, Folder 43)
  - 1870 Oct - Nov (Box 42, Folder 44)
  - 1870 Dec - 1871 Jan (Box 42, Folder 45)
  - 1871 Feb - Mar (Box 42, Folder 46)
  - 1871 Apr - May (Box 42, Folder 47)
  - 1871 Jun - Aug (Box 42, Folder 48)
  - 1871 Sep - Dec 9 (Box 42, Folder 49)
  - [mid-1872] (Box 42, Folder 50)
  - 1871 Dec 10 - 1872 May (Box 42, Folder 51)
  - 1872 Jun - Dec (Vol. 7) (Box 42, Folder 52)
  - 1872 Dec - 1873 Mar (Vol. 8) (Box 42, Folder 53)
  - 1873 Apr - Jun (Vol. 9) (Box 42, Folder 54)
  - 1873 [June?] - Sep 22 (Vol. 10) (Box 42, Folder 55)
  - [late 1873] (Box 42, Folder 56)
  - 1874 Jan - Apr (Vol. 12) (Box 42, Folder 57)
  - [mid-1874] (Box 42, Folder 58)
  - 1874 Jul - Dec 18 (Vol. 14) (Box 42, Folder 59)
  - 1877 Jan - Feb (Vol. 16) (Box 42, Folder 60)
  - 1877 Mar - Sep 5 (Vol. 17) (Box 42, Folder 61)
  - 1878 Jan 31 - 1879 Feb (Vol. 18) (Box 42, Folder 62)
  - 1879 Mar - 1880 Aug (Vol. 19) (Box 42, Folder 63)
  - 1880 Sep - 1881 Jan (Vol. 20) (Box 42, Folder 64)
  - 1881 Feb - Apr (Vol. 21) (Box 42, Folder 65)
  - 1881 Aug - Oct (Vol. 23) (Box 42, Folder 66)
  - 1881 Nov - Dec (Vol. 24) (Box 42, Folder 67)
  - 1882 Jan - Mar (Vol. 25) (Box 42, Folder 68)
  - 1882 Apr - Jun (Vol. 26) (Box 42, Folder 69)
  - 1882 Jul - Nov (Vol. 27) (Box 42, Folder 70)
  - 1882 Dec - 1883 Apr (Vol. 28) (Box 42, Folder 71)
  - 1883 May - Oct (Vol. 29) (Box 42, Folder 72)
  - 1883 Nov - 1884 Oct (Vol. 30) (Box 42, Folder 73)
  - 1884 Nov - 1885 Jun (Vol. 31) (Box 42, Folder 74)
  - 1885 Jul - 1886 Jan 27 (Vol. 32) (Box 42, Folder 75)
  - 1886 Jan 28 - Jun 28 (Vol. 33) (Box 42, Folder 76)
  - 1886 Jun 29 - Dec (Vol. 34) (Box 42, Folder 77)
  - 1887 Jan - Jul 20 (Vol. 35) (Box 42, Folder 78)
  - 1887 July 20 - Dec (Vol. 36) (Box 42, Folder 79)
  - 1888 Jan - Jun (Vol. 37) (Box 42, Folder 80)
  - 1888 Jul - Aug (Box 42, Folder 81)
  - 1889 Feb - 1888 Sep (Vol. 38) (Box 42, Folder 82)
  - 1889 Mar - Aug (Vol. 39) (Box 42, Folder 83)
  - 1889 Sep - 1890 Feb 10 (Vol. 40) (Box 42, Folder 84)
  - 1890 Feb 11 - Jun 25 (Vol. 41) (Box 42, Folder 85)
  - 1890 Jun 25 - 1891 Jan 17 (Vol. 42) (Box 42, Folder 86)
  - 1891 Jan 17 - Jun 19 (Vol. 43) (Box 42, Folder 87)
  - 1891 Jun 20 - 1892 Jan (Vol. 44) (Box 42, Folder 88)
  - 1892 Jan - Jul (Vol. 45) (Box 42, Folder 89)
  - 1892 Jul - 1893 Jan (Vol. 46) (Box 42, Folder 90)
  - 1893 Feb - May (Vol. 47) (Box 42, Folder 91)
  - 1893 Jun - 1894 Jan (Vol. 48) (Box 42, Folder 92)
  - 1894 Jan 21 - Apr 28 (Vol. 49) (Box 42, Folder 93)
  - 1894 Apr - Aug (Vol. 50) (Box 42, Folder 94)
  - 1894 June 15 - Oct (Box 42, Folder 95)
  - 1894 Jul - Dec (Box 42, Folder 96)
  - 1895 Jan - Feb (Vol. 53) (Box 42, Folder 97)
  - 1895 Feb - May (Vol. 54) (Box 42, Folder 98)
  - 1895 May - Sep (Vol. 55) (Box 42, Folder 99)
  - 1895 Sep - Dec (Vol. 56) (Box 42, Folder 100)
  - [1895 Dec - 1896 Feb?] (Vol. 57) (Box 42, Folder 101)
  - 1896 Feb - Jul (Vol. 58) (Box 42, Folder 102)
  - 1896 Jul - Nov (Vol. 59) (Box 42, Folder 103)
  - 1896 Nov - 1897 Jan (Vol. 60) (Box 42, Folder 104)
  - 1897 Jan - Mar (Vol. 61) (Box 42, Folder 105)
  - 1897 Mar - Jul (Vol. 62) (Box 42, Folder 106)
  - 1897 Jul - Nov (Vol. 63) (Box 42, Folder 107)
  - 1897 Nov - 1898 Feb (Vol. 64) (Box 42, Folder 108)
  - 1898 Feb - Apr (Vol. 65) (Box 42, Folder 109)
  - 1898 May - Sep (Vol. 66) (Box 42, Folder 110)
  - 1898 Aug - Dec (Vol. 67) (Box 42, Folder 111)
  - 1898 Nov - 1899 Feb (Vol. 68) (Box 42, Folder 112)
  - [1899 Jan - Apr] (Box 42, Folder 113)
  - 1899 Jan - 1900 Mar (Vol. 70) (Box 42, Folder 114)
  - [mid-1899] (Box 42, Folder 115)
  - [1899-1900?] (Box 42, Folder 116)
  - 1900 Mar 23 - 1902 Jan 30 (Vol. 71) (Box 42, Folder 117)
  - 1900 Feb 15 - Aug 25 (Vol. 72) (Box 42, Folder 118)
  - 1900 Sep 4 - 1901 Jan 12 (Vol. 73) (Box 42, Folder 119)
  - [1901 Jan 23 - May 29] (Vol. 74) (Box 42, Folder 120)
  - [1901 Jun 7 - 1902 Jan 25] (Vol. 75) (Box 42, Folder 121)
  - [1902 Jan 14 - April 30] (Vol. 76) (Box 42, Folder 122)
  - [1902 May 2 - Sep 25] (Vol. 77) (Box 42, Folder 123)
  - [undated] (Box 42, Folder 124)
  - [undated] (Box 42, Folder 125)
  - [undated] (Box 42, Folder 126)
  - [undated] (Box 42, Folder 127)
  - Index to Letters Received-Vol. 1-77 (Volume-folio 1)
  - Index to Letters Received-Sept. 1902-1909 (Volume-folio 2)
  - Freedman's Bureau Index to Letters Received (incomplete) (Volume-folio 3)
  - Notes on letters received and answered - 1866-1868 (Volume 4)
  - Letters Received [abstracts]-Vol. I-Apr. 1868-Dec. 1869 (Volume-folio 5)
  - Letters Received [abstracts]-Vol. II-Jan. 1870-Dec. 1871 (Volume-folio 6)
  - Letters Received [abstracts]-Vol. III-Jan. 1872-Jun. 1875 (Volume-folio 7)
  - Index to scrapbooks (Volume-folio 8)
- M91.10: Military career, records, 1854-1909, undated, M91.10; 0.25 linear feet
  Documents, reports, orders, manuscript and printed records, etc., from 1854 to 1909, concerning Howard's military career. Organized into general groupings of Military, Freedmen's Bureau, and Indians. Included are Howard's first army commission (signed by Jefferson Davis) and various military orders; information on freedmen's organizations, including the Freedman's Bank; and records concerning Native Americans, including reports of negotiations with the Apaches.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Military, general. Army vouchers, certificates, etc., 1872 - 1902 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Military, general. Blacks in the military, 1873 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Military, general. Chickamauga and Chattanooga National Park Commission, 1900 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Military, general. Civil War, re Confederate soldiers (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Military, general. Civil War memorials, groups or individuals, 1873 - 1899 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Military, general. Commission of Howard as 2nd Lt. of Ordnance (signed by Jefferson Davis), 1854 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Military, general. Congressional bills, 1899 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Military, general. Courts-martial and military investigations material (subpoenas, etc.), 1867 - 1874 (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Military, general. Department of Arizona, report by O.B. Wilcox, 1880 (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - Military, general. International Military Match (Box 43, Folder 10)
  - Military, general. Military colleges, 1895 (Box 43, Folder 11)
  - Military, general. Miscellaneous material, 1877 - 1894 and undated (Box 43, Folder 12)
  - Military, general. Orders - Commonwealth of Massachusetts, Adj. Gen's office, 1889 - 1890 (Box 43, Folder 13)
  - Military, general. Orders - manuscript, 1856 - 1893 (Box 43, Folder 14)
  - Military, general. Orders - presidential, 1877 (Box 43, Folder 15)
  - Military, general. Orders - printed, 1864 - 1901 (Box 43, Folder 16)
  - Military, general. Orders - State of New Jersey, Adj. Gen.'s office, 1894 (Box 43, Folder 17)
  - Military, general. Organizations, Grand Army of the Republic (national and regional posts), 1867 - 1891 (Box 43, Folder 18)
  - Military, general. Organizations, Grand Army of the Republic - U.S. Grant Post #327 (NYC), 1889 - 1894 (Box 43, Folder 19)
  - Military, general. Organizations, Loyal Legion, 1885 - 1909 (Box 43, Folder 20)
  - Military, general. Organizations, Medal of Honor Legion, 1899 (Box 43, Folder 21)
  - Military, general. Organizations, Miscellaneous, 1886 - 1898: Army Mutual Aid Association; 11th Army Corps Association; Military Service Institution; New York State Society of the Cincinnati; Old Guard Association; U.S. Cavalry Association; Veterans of the Blue and Gray; Veterans of the Mexican War; War Veterans Club (Box 43, Folder 22)
  - Military, general. Organizations, National Guard of California, 1887 (Box 43, Folder 23)
  - Military, general. Organizations, National Home for Disabled Volunteer Soldiers, 1893 - 1898 (Box 43, Folder 24)
  - Military, general. Organizations, Society of the Army of the Tennessee; ... of the Cumberland; ... of the Potomac, 1865 - 1893 (Box 43, Folder 25)
  - Military, general. Organizations, Women's Relief Corps (GAR Women's Auxiliary) - Speech by Harriet K. Scott, etc., 1894 (Box 43, Folder 26)
  - Military, general. Patents, games, etc. (Box 43, Folder 27)
  - Military, general. Petitions re the Dalles Military Road, 1875 (Box 43, Folder 28)
  - Military, general. West Point - ephemera concerning Howard as Cadet, 1854 - 1854 (Box 43, Folder 29)
  - Freedmen's Bureau. American Freedman's and Union Commission, semi-monthly report of the corres. sec'y of the Exec. Board of - 1866 Mar 14 (Box 43, Folder 30)
  - Freedmen's Bureau. Certificates and orders, 1868 - 1873 (Box 43, Folder 31)
  - Freedmen's Bureau. Miscellaneous manuscript records, 1866 - 1873. (Box 43, Folder 32)
  - Freedmen's Bureau. Missing or deficient office records, 1873 (Box 43, Folder 33)
  - Freedmen's Bureau. National Freedman's Savings and Trust, 1866 - 1871 (Box 43, Folder 34)
  - Freedmen's Bureau. re freedmen - manuscript (Box 43, Folder 35)
  - Freedmen's Bureau. re freedmen - printed (Box 43, Folder 36)
  - Freedmen's Bureau. Retained bounty fund, statement of Edward S. Fowler, 1874 (Box 43, Folder 37)
  - Indians. Campaigns, Battle of Clearwater - transcript of the record of Capt. A.G. Forse (Box 43, Folder 38)
  - Indians. Documents establishing or concerning "Cochise Apache Reservation" and "Chiracahua Reservation," 1872 [manuscript copies] (Box 43, Folder 39)
  - Indians. Fragment of a report on an interview between Howard, Eskimenzin, Esketella, and Miguel (Chief of Apaches) concerning Agt. Jacobs [1872?] (Box 43, Folder 40)
  - Indians. Map of White Mountain Apache Indian Reservation - 1872 Dec 20 [manuscript] (Box 43, Folder 41)
  - Indians. Petition re the Piute Indians by Sarah Winnemucca Hopkins [text only] (Box 43, Folder 42)
  - Indians. Report of a peace council between the Navajo Indians and the Apaches (Box 43, Folder 43)
- M91.11: Religious and educational work, records, 1857-1902, undated, M91.11; 24.0 folders
  Documents, reports, pamphlets, handbills,, and other records, from 1857 to 1902, concerning Howard's life-long interests in religious and educational work. He helped found several churches, most notably the First Parish Congregational Church in Washington, and educational institutions, especially Howard University and Lincoln Memorial University. His interests extended to missionary and religious associations like the Congregational Home Mission Society and the Young Men's Christian Association.
  - Religion - Associations. American Board of Commissioners of Foreign Missions, report of unknown ABCFM missionary about his expulsion after the 1894 Armenian massacre at Bitlis, 1897 (Box 43, Folder 44)
  - Religion - Associations. American Home Missionary Society, 1892 (Box 43, Folder 45)
  - Religion - Associations. American Sabbath Union, Constitution (Box 43, Folder 46)
  - Religion - Associations. Camp Memorial Church (NYC) and Camp Mission, 1859 - 1881 (Box 43, Folder 47)
  - Religion - Associations. Congregational Home Missionary Society, 1897 (Box 43, Folder 48)
  - Religion - Associations. Evangelical Alliance (Box 43, Folder 49)
  - Religion - Associations. Miscellaneous commissions, conventions, 1869 - 1898 (Box 43, Folder 50)
  - Religion - Associations. Petitions re (Box 43, Folder 51)
  - Religion - Associations. U.S. Christian Commission, 1865 (Box 43, Folder 52)
  - Religion - Associations. YMCA (national and state chapters) (Box 43, Folder 53)
  - Religion - Associations. Certification of Howard as member of the M.E.C., Tampa, 1857 (Box 43, Folder 54)
  - Religion - Churches. First Parish Congregational Church of Washington - financial material, 1866 - 1868 (Box 43, Folder 55)
  - Religion - Churches. First Parish Congregational Church of Washington - miscellaneous, 1867 - 1876 (Box 43, Folder 56)
  - Religion - Churches. First Presbyterian Church (Wash.), 1867 (Box 43, Folder 57)
  - Education. Associations (Box 43, Folder 58)
  - Education. Bowdoin related items, 1882-1897 (Box 43, Folder 59)
  - Education. "Education of the Colored Man" [electrostatic copy] (Box 43, Folder 60)
  - Education. Institutions. Howard University - manuscript, 1873 - 1894 (Box 43, Folder 61)
  - Education. Institutions. Howard University - printed, 1874 - 1892 (Box 43, Folder 62)
  - Education. Institutions. Lake Charles College, 1896 (Box 43, Folder 63)
  - Education. Institutions. Lincoln Memorial University, The Folk of the Cumberland Gap, by O.O. Howard, 1902 (Box 43, Folder 64)
  - Education. Institutions. Lincoln Memorial University - reports, accounts, etc., 1899 - 1900 (Box 43, Folder 65)
  - Education. Institutions. Miscellaneous: Berea College (Berea, Ky.); Mm. Clerc & Miss Peck's ... School for Girls (Phil, Pa.); Franklin Academy (Franklin, Neb.); Hampton Institute; Maryville College (Maryville, Tn.); North Carolina Military Institute (Charlotte, NC); Pacific Theological Seminary (Oakland, Ca.); St. Timothy's Hall (Catonsville, Md.); South Carolina University (Box 43, Folder 66)
  - Education. Institutions. Thousand Island Park Program, 1892 (Box 43, Folder 67)
- M91.12: Financial records, 1855-1909, M91.12; 11.0 folders
  Bills, receipts, documents and business records, from 1855 to 1909, relating to Howard's personal finances, and his business and real estate investments. Included are records relating to his insurance premiums, loans, book royalties, and association dues.
  - Business records and documents. Boynton Bicycle Railway Company, 1893 (Box 43, Folder 68)
  - Business records and documents. Florida Mining and Colonization Company, 1892 (Box 43, Folder 69)
  - Bills and receipts. General, 1866 - 1909 (Box 43, Folder 70)
  - Bills and receipts. Life and annuity insurance companies, 1869 - 1889 (Box 43, Folder 71)
  - Bills and receipts. Loans to, from or countersigned by Howard, 1871 - 1885 (Box 43, Folder 72)
  - Bills and receipts. Post office department, 1881 - 1883 (Box 43, Folder 73)
  - Bills and receipts. Publishers and booksellers, 1879 - 1897 (Box 43, Folder 74)
  - Bills and receipts. Stocks, etc., 1881 - 1897 (Box 43, Folder 75)
  - Bills and receipts. Religious, missionary and military organizations, 1870 - 1900 (Box 43, Folder 76)
  - Real estate owned by Howard, documents and ephemera, 1866 - 1900 (Box 43, Folder 77)
  - Real estate not owned by Howard, surveys, etc., 1855 - 1898 (Box 43, Folder 78)
- M91.13: Personal records, 1866-1900, undated, M91.13; 0.5 linear feet
  Printed and manuscript records, from 1840 to 1908, relating to Howard's personal interests. Although there is a little overlap with other non-correspondence series, the personal records include biographical information on Howard and others, contracts and prospectuses relating to Howards writings, and material concerning his interests in temperance and political issues.
  - Associations. American Exhibitor's Agency Co. (for 1900 Paris Exposition) (Box 43, Folder 79)
  - Associations. Miscellaneous (American Institute of Civics, National Historical Museum, Thronatieska Club of Associated Hunters, The Drawing Room) (Box 43, Folder 80)
  - Associations. National Geographic Society (Box 43, Folder 81)
  - Associations. Society of American Authors and Association of American Authors (Box 43, Folder 82)
  - Associations. World's Congress Auxiliary of the World's Columbian Exposition (Box 43, Folder 83)
  - Biographical material. re Howard (Box 43, Folder 84)
  - Biographical material. Bowdoin College Alumni Office and News Service write-ups (Box 43, Folder 85)
  - Biographical material. "Glory and Grace: The Civil War Career of the 'Christian General,' Oliver Otis Howard" by Judith Relaford (Box 43, Folder 86)
  - Biographical material. ms biographical material on Howard (Box 43, Folder 87)
  - Biographical material. Material relating to Mr. Webb's unfinished biography of OOH (folder 1/2) (Box 43, Folder 88)
  - Biographical material. Material relating to Mr. Webb's unfinished biography of OOH (folder 2/2) (Box 43, Folder 89)
  - Biographical material. re various people, including: Carlin, William P.; Dilger, Hubert; Eaton, D.L.; Former, Thomas and Martha; Gould, A.H.; Hildt, George H.; Howard, Chancey Otis; Howard, Rowland Bailey; Kiddoo, J.B.; Lewis, Edmonia; McClellan, John; Miles, Nelson A.; Osborn, T.W.; Pearsons, D.K.; Runkle, Benjamin P.; Safford, A.P.K.; Spurgin, David G.; Treat, Charles Gould (Box 43, Folder 90)
  - Clippings. re Howard (Box 43, Folder 91)
  - Clippings. of interest to Howard (folder 1/2) (Box 43, Folder 92)
  - Clippings. of interest to Howard (folder 2/2) (Box 43, Folder 93)
  - Documents. General (Box 43, Folder 94)
  - Documents. Passports, related items (Box 43, Folder 95)
  - Ephemera. General, manuscript (Box 43, Folder 96)
  - Ephemera. General, printed (Box 43, Folder 97)
  - Ephemera. Invitation to visit the Maine State Legislature, 1866 (Box 43, Folder 98)
  - Ephemera. Map of Slave routes in the Near East from the supplement to the "Anti-Slavery Reporter" - 1880 Sep (Box 43, Folder 99)
  - Ephemera. Memorial of the Port Townsend Chamber of Commerce on the subject of coast defenses (Box 43, Folder 100)
  - Ephemera. Miscellaneous fragments (Box 43, Folder 101)